<resources>
    <string name="app_name">DevBhoomi Uttarakhand</string>
    <string name="textview">\n\n\t\t\t<b><u>Biodiversity Of Uttarakhand</u></b>\n
        \n\t\t\t\t\tUttarakhand the 27th state of Republic of India lies between 28° 44\' and 31° 28\' N Latitude and 77° 35\' and 81° 01\' E longitude. It was carved out of UP on 9ᵗʰ November 2000. The geographical area of the state is 53483 sq. km and the terrain and topography of the state is largely hilly with large areas under snow cover and steep slopes.\n \nUttarakhand State comprises of 02 regions 13 districts, 78 Tehsils and 95 community development blocks. The districts lying in Garhwal Region are Uttarkashi, Chamoli, Pauri, Rudraprayag, Tehri, Dehradun and Haridwar and the remaining 06 in Kumaon Region are Udham Singh Nagar, Nainital, Almora, Pithoragarh, Champawat and Bageshwar. The human population of the State is 1.01 Crore (2001) compared to 25.18 lacs in 1951 and that of livestock is 50.22 lacs in 2012 as compared to 41.68 lacs (1993).\n

 \nUttarkashi, Chamoli and Pithoragarh districts of Uttarakhand share International boundary in the NW with China. In the east, the districts of Pithoragarh, Champawat and Udham Singh Nagar also share International boundary with Nepal. Uttarkashi and Dehradun share inter-state boundaries with Himachal Pradesh in the north-west, while Dehradun, Haridwar, part of Nainital and Udham Singh Nagar touches the boundary of Uttar Pradesh in the south.\n

 \nThe Garhwal Himalayas along with Kumaon and a part of Himachal Pradesh has unique characteristics as it has Tibet in the north, Upper Gangetic Plain in the south and Eastern Himalayan provinces in the east. Physiographically, Uttarakhand represents a cross-section of the Himalaya on the basis of its evolutionary history, namely the Trans-Himalaya, Greater Himalaya or Himadri, Lesser Himalaya, Shiwalik Ranges, foothills and Terai and the Plains of Dehradun, Haridwar and Udham Singh Nagar.\n

\nThe floral and faunal composition is diverse and interesting. Between the Himalaya in the north and the hills and the plateau in the south lies a vast Gangetic Plains which is one of the largest homogenous alluvial plains in the world. In Uttarakhand, the Bhabar skirts the Shiwaliks mainly in Garhwal and Nainital- Pilibhit while the Terai extends from River Yamuna on the west and a large portion of it lies in the Nepal. The Terai in Uttarakhand covers lower portion of district Nainital.\n

\nMajor portion of the state is mountainous and these mountains (Himalayas) are one of the youngest mountain systems of the world (40 million years in age compared to peninsular mountains of 1500-2500 million years old) and hence ecologically very fragile and relatively much more susceptible to earthquakes and landslides. Shiwalik formations are one of the most important eco-region due to their endemicity and past geological history. The era of Shiwalik ecosystem of rocks is called “Age of Mammals”. It is the filtering zone for migration of fauna and flora from highlands to lowlands and vice-versa. It is not only a gateway to the enhanced biodiversity but also to the green and white revolutions, industrialization and creation of livelihood opportunities. This region harbored a rich fauna in the geological past as evidenced by the discovery of fossils of Amphibians, Reptiles and Mammals. The wide altitudinal range is the richest zone in terms of habitat and biodiversity.\n

\nUttarakhand has everything except the sea. India, Indonesia, and the Indian Ocean cover the area once occupied by the Tethys ocean, and Turkey, Iraq, and Tibet sit on Cimmeria. What was once the Tethys Sea has become the Mediterranean sea. But discovery of the Ammonite fossils in the upper reaches of Himalayas, in Nanda Devi are suggestive of the fact that area was perhaps submerged under Tethys Sea in the geological past.  Hence, the occurrence of the marine biodiversity in the fossil form is also contributing to the richness of the faunal diversity in Uttarakhand.\n

\nThe state is represented by biographic zone 2B Western Himalaya and 7B Shiwaliks consisting of Kumaon and Garhwal regions. Total geographical area of the state (53,483 sq.km) is 1.6 % of the total geographical area of the Country, out of which 46,035 sq.km is hilly. The major wealth of the state is its forests with very rich biodiversity. The state ranks sixth among the other states in terms of percentage of recorded forest area. The state has thus varied terrain, major portion of which is mountainous with unique ecological diversity consisting of high alpine areas to the Sub-tropical and Tropical regions. Total Forest cover area in the state is 3.47 million ha constituting 71% of the State’s Geographical area. The forest diversity of the state comprises of Tropical Moist Forest (500-1000m) which is Terai and Bhabar belt of Sub Himalayan Tract, Sub-Tropical Pine Forest (1000-2000m), Himalayan Moist Temperate Forest (2000-3000m), Sub-Alpine Forests (3400-4000m) and Alpine Forests  4000-5000m). \nPhysiographically, the state can be divided into three zones namely, the Himalaya, The Shiwalik and the Tarai Region. The state has a temperate climate except in plain areas where the climate is tropical. The average annual rainfall is 1550 mm.\n

\nEnormous floristic and vegetation diversity marks the upper limit of vegetation, with variety of orchids, horticulture and economic plants, including Bamboo, wild germplasm of some cultivated species. By virtue of its extensive geographical stretch, varied terrain and climate the Himalayan Mountain Ranges in Uttarakhand are bestowed with a series of wetlands. Important perennial rivers are Ganga, Yamuna, Bhagirathi, Alaknanda, Ramganga, Nayar, Kosi, Saryu, Sharda and their tributaries. These wetlands, which are some of the most productive and endangered ecosystems, exhibit tremendous faunal diversity from Protozoa to Mammalia. They are roosting and breeding grounds and shelters for migratory and resident birds during various times of the year.\n

\nWith abounding diversity on all accounts, the biodiversity of the State is bound to be rich. After the creation of Uttarakhand, as many as 3748 faunal species were inventoried and documented which included 451 species and sub-species, two new Taxa, 22 constitute a first record for India. Ten species occurring in the state are endemic to India. The faunal species included 1060 species of vertebrates, 2020 species of Insecta Invertebrates and  4346 invertebrates excluding Insecta.\n

\nThe present state of the Uttarakhand conforms to its rich heritage status supported by a rich floral diversity, vegetation, forest cover, healthy and pristine ecosystem and tremendous conservation efforts from species level to genetic level and to ecosystem level. Due to its unique bio-diversity, the state is also home to several rare and endangered species of herbal and aromatic plants. Realizing the immense potential of this resource in the state, the state government has declared Uttarakhand as a Herbal State.\n</string>
    <string name="Threats">\n\n<b><u>Threats to Biodiversity</u></b>\n\n As  Uttarakhand  is  a  newly  formed  state,  many  developmental  and planning projects have been proposed or will be proposed in the near future by the government. It would be a great threat to the biodiversity of the state if one does not take into account the possible impacts of these projects. The major possible issues to the biodiversity of the regions are given below :\n
        \na) Habitat degradation for illegal, commercial and developmental purposes\n
        \nb) Deliberate forest fires\n
        \nc) Overgrazing of grass that also leads to soil degradation\n
        \nd) Diversion of forest land for non-forest purposes\n
        \ne) Exotic species and weed infestation that is not suitable for indigenous species\n
        \nf) Over exploitation of the flora for medicinal purposes, or for timber has le to the extinction of flora and loss of habitat of fauna.\n
        \ng) Faulty  agricultural  practices and  indiscriminate  use  of  fertilizers and pesticides\n
        \nh) Mining\n
        \ni) Introduction of hydroelectric projects\n
        \nj) Pollution in waterbodies\n
        \nk) Mismanagement  of  water  resources  leading  to  loss  of  aquatic biodiversity\n
        \nl) Tourism is the major cause of pollution\n
        \nm) Road and railway construction leads to loss of natural forests as well as of animals (due to accidents)\n
        \nn) Poaching and illegal trading of wildlife products\n
        \no) Climate change  Conservation strategies and policies Biodiversity is important for our existence as well as for the well-being of  any  particular  region  because  it  provides  the  fundamental  building blocks  for  the  many  goods  and  services.\n\n
    Natural Resources and Biodiversity of Uttarakhand environment to lead our basic life. Therefore, it is our duty to take care of  the  biodiversity,  so  that it  would  remain  healthy.  But  unfortunately, biodiversity  has  been  adversely  affected  due  to  the  malpractices  of  a human. A number of initiatives have been taken by the government for its preservation and  also many awareness programs have  been conducted to aware the people about its utility. Uttarakhand government is also aware of the implications  of threats  caused by  the biodiversity degradation hence, many important initiatives have been implied to conserve the biodiversity by developing protected  area network, national parks,  wildlife centuries, Medicinal  Plant  Conservation  Areas  (MPCAS),  herbal  gardens, arboretums, parks, and zoos.\n
        \nIn Uttarakhand, there are a total of 6 national parks, 6 wildlife sanctuaries, 1 biosphere reserve, 1 world heritage site, 2 elephant  ranges  and  2  conservation  reserves,  covering  an  area  of  0.73 million hectares and comprising of 13.68% of the state’s total geographical area [10] the various goals of conservation strategies are as follows : \n                 \na) Conserving the natural heritage of the state, including the unique, rich biodiversity,  and  fragile  ecosystems,  such  as  forests,  grasslands, wetlands, and mountains;  wild and domesticated biodiversity; genetic resources and ecological and environmental processes.\n
        \nb) Giving  priority  to  in  situ conservation  of  the  state’s  biological  and cultural  diversity  located  both  within  and  outside  the state’s  protected areas.\n
        \nc) Ex  situ  conservation  of  flora,  fauna,  and  floral  and  faunal  genetic resources.\n \nd) Developing strategies  and actions  for the  conservation of agriculture, livestock, fodder and ethnobotanical diversity.\n \ne) Using biodiversity and natural resources sustainably.    National Board for Wildlife (NBWL) provides the policy framework for  wildlife  conservation  in  the  country.  National  Wildlife  Action  Plan 2002-2016  has  been  proposed  for  wildlife  conservation  through  people’s involvement.  In  this  regard,  a  number  of  acts  have  been  implemented namely,  Indian  Forest  Act  1927,  Wildlife  (Protection)Act  1972,  Forest (Conservation) Act 1980, Environment (Protection)  Act 1986, Biological.\n
        \nNatural Resources and Biodiversity of Uttarakhand  Diversity Act, 2002 and  Recognition of Forest Rights Act, 2006. In Uttarakhand,  Forest  Department  works  as  a  nodal  agency  that  implies different central schemes related to  biodiversity conservation in the state such  as  the  implementation  of  Integrated  Development  of  Wildlife Habitats, Project Tiger, Project Elephant, etc. Due to the rich biodiversity of  state,  several  significant  measures  have  been  taken  into  account  by central as well as state government as given below :\n  \na) First National Park in the Asian Mainland (Corbett National Park)\n  \nb) Govind Wildlife Sanctuary\n  \nc) Kedarnath Wildlife Sanctuary\n  \nd) Valley of Flowers National Park  \ne) Project Elephant in Rajaji National Park\n  \nf) Project Tiger in Corbett National Park\n  \ng) Nanda Devi Biosphere Reserve (India’s second Biosphere Reserve)\n  \nh) Asan Wetland and Jhilmiltal conservation reserves\n  \ni) Uttarakhand Biodiversity Act, 2002  j) Establishment of State Medicinal Plant Board (SMPB)\n  \nk) Wild Life Advisory Board\n  \nl) Medicinal Plant Conservation Areas (MPCAs)\n  \nm) Establishment of Anti-Poaching Unit\n \nn) Establishment  of  first  Aquatic  Biodiversity  Conservation  Zone  of Uttarakhand has been proposed</string>
    <string name="conservations">\n\n1. Conservation of the natural heritage of the State including the unique, biodiversity rich and fragile ecosystems of the State such as forests, grasslands, wetlands and mountain ecosystems and their species including wild and domesticated biodiversity, genetic resources and ecological and environmental processes.\n
\n2. Primacy to be given to in situ conservation of the State’s biological and cultural diversity located both within and outside the State’s protected areas.\n
        \n3. Identification of major threats to biodiversity in Uttarakhand and identification of ecosystems and habitats important for conservation lying outside Protected Area Network and suggest ways to protect and manage them.\n
\n4. Assessment of adequacy of conservation and management measures, plans, socio-economic aspects, research and monitoring needs for Protected Areas and Non Protected Areas such as reserved, protected and unclassified forests, fresh water and other wetland systems, avifauna wintering areas, agricultural ecosystems, landscape systems and sites of anthropogenic importance.\n
\n5. Linking biodiversity with livelihood of local people.\n
\n6. Assessment of the status and effectiveness of ex- situ conservation in the State including rehabilitation of endangered and threatened species and captive breeding programmes and per mote ex- situ conservation of flora, fauna and their genetic resources.\n
\n7. Biodiversity education, training, awareness, public outreach, skills development and involvement of voluntary sector.\n
\n8. Review of laws, policies, institutions, regulatory structures and procedures including cross-sectoral coordination and cooperation in relation to biodiversity conservation and sustainable use, assessment of effectiveness of wildlife protection in controlling the trade in wildlife products including medicinal plants and law enforcement and coordination between agencies.\n
\n9. Focus on developing mechanism for people oriented sustainable management and sustainable use of biological resources, and for that constitute “Biodiversity Management Committees (BMCs)” at the level of all Local Bodies and prepare “People’s Biodiversity Register (PBR)” for each BMC.\n
\n10. Develop mechanism for equitable sharing of benefits with the BMCs arising of the utilization of biological resources.\n
\n11. Document traditional knowledge at the local level and develop mechanism for their conservation and utilization.\n
\n12. Develop strategies and actions for conservation of agriculture, livestock, fodder and ethno botanical diversity.\n
\n13. Development that is compatible with sustainable use of natural resources.\n
\n14. Biodiversity as integral to human-existence and permeating developmental planning and implementation.\n
\n15. Per mote culturally sensitive conservation and management that recognizes and protects traditional knowledge and resource use.\n
\n16. Pursuit of a landscape and ecosystem approach.\n
\n17. Meeting of the State’s forest based needs of fuel wood, fodder, timber, Non Wood Forest Produce etc. from non-forest areas and degraded forest lands by encouraging afforestation, plantations etc.\n
\n18. Encouraging and providing incentives for private and public sector investments.\n
\n19. Creation of a just and equitable society based on sustainable resource use.</string>
    <string name="textviewFloral">
        \n\t\t\tUttarakhand is the state located at the foothills of the snow clad Himalayas with lush
green vegetation. There is a diverse range of flora and fauna habitated in Uttarakhand. The
State has rich and diverse floral, faunal and microbial wealth including rare and threatened
species of plants and animals.\n
\nTraditionally, the mountains in the lower regions of Uttarakhand were covered with moist
deciduous forest. Between elevations of 1,500-3,000m, the major natural vegetation entails of
Pine, Oak, Rhododendron, Walnut and Larch. Below the snow line, the vegetation consists of
forests of Spruce, Fir, Cypress, Juniper and Birch, while above the snow line (in the higher
altitude of the State) is Alpine vegetation which includes Mosses, Lichen and a diversity of
wildflowers such as Blue Poppies and Edelweiss. As a result of deforestation, much of the
original fauna of the Himalayas are restricted to protected areas and sanctuaries.\n
        \n
    </string>
    <string name="textviewfloral">\n\t\t\tUttarakhand is the state located at the foothills of the snow clad Himalayas with lush
        green vegetation. There is a diverse range of flora and fauna habitated in Uttarakhand. The
        State has rich and diverse floral, faunal and microbial wealth including rare and threatened
    species of plants and animals.\n
    \nTraditionally, the mountains in the lower regions of Uttarakhand were covered with moist
    deciduous forest. Between elevations of 1,500-3,000m, the major natural vegetation entails of
    Pine, Oak, Rhododendron, Walnut and Larch. Below the snow line, the vegetation consists of
    forests of Spruce, Fir, Cypress, Juniper and Birch, while above the snow line (in the higher
    altitude of the State) is Alpine vegetation which includes Mosses, Lichen and a diversity of
    wildflowers such as Blue Poppies and Edelweiss. As a result of deforestation, much of the
    original fauna of the Himalayas are restricted to protected areas and sanctuaries.\n </string>

    <string name="textviewfloral1">
        \nIn Floral diversity point of view, Uttarakhand falls under the West Himalayan Biogeographic
zone, situated in the lap of the Himalaya ther region is rich in forest wealth that ranges from
subtropical to Alpine types.The flora and vegetation of the state ranges from tropical deciduous
to alpine vegetation; broadly catagorised into three mazor types :\n</string>
    <string name="textviewfloral2">
        \n\t<b><u>1. Sub-Tropical Zone of Uttarakhand</u></b>\n
The sub-tropical zone has pure as well as mixed forests of Shore Robusta (Sa I), the others
being Lannea coromandelica (Jhingan), Buchanania lanzan,Dalbergia disso (Shisham), Haldina cordifolia (Haldu),Syzygium cumini (Jamun), Mallotus philippinensis (Rohini),Mitragyna parvifolia, Terminalia spp. (Myrobalans), Ficus spp.(Figs), Macaranga pustulata, Callicarpa arborea,Diopoknema butyracea (Chyura), Bauhinia variegate(Kachnar), Bomb ax cobia (Semal), Lydia claying (Pula),Schleicher oleos (Kokum), Holoptelea integrities (Karanj),Cassia fistula (Amaltas), Nyctanthes arbor-tristis (Parijat),
Anogeissus latifolia (Bakli, Dhaura), etc. The shrubby vegetation is represented by Murrayakoenigii, Carissa opaca, Clerodendrum viscous, Adhatoda vasica, Jasminum multiflorum, Solanumerianthum, Cal/icarpa macrophylla, Eranthemum nervosum, Phlogacanthus thyrsiformis, Jatrophacurcas, Rhus parviflora, Dodonaea viscosa, Woodfordia fruticosa and many others.\n</string>
    <string name="textviewfloral3">
        \n\t\t<b><u>2. Temperate Zone of Uttarakhand</u></b>\n
The Temperate zone is marked by the presence of Quercus
leucotrichophora (Banj oak), Rhododendron arboretum (Burans), Myrica
esculent a (Kaphal), Leonia ovalifolia (Aynor), Ibex dipyrena, Quercus
semecarpifolia (Kharsu Oak), Q. dilatata (Moru Oak), etc. The coniferous
forests in this zone are unique. Pure stands of Pinus roxburghii (Chir Pine)
and Cadres deodar (Deodar, Cedar), Abides windrow (Raga), Pinus
wal/ichiana (Kail), Taxus wal/ichiana (Thuner, Himalayan Yew) at places
give a pristine look to the slopes. The slopes in temperate zone also have
insectivorous plants like Drosera peltata and species of Utricularia. Another
such species is Pinguicula alpina seen in Martoli Bugyal, Kumaon.\n
        \nThe Saprophytes and Parasites are also well represented by Monotropa
unit/ora, Dendrophthoe falcata (Banda), Balanophora in volucrata, and
species of Viscum, Korthalsella, Arceuthobium, Scurrula, etc. The zone has a
variety of useful plants, some of them well known for centuries. These include Cedrus deodar a,
Pinus spp., Abies pindrow, Quercus spp., Aconitum heterophyllum, Paeonia emodi, Swertia
chirayita, Bergenia ciliata, Dioscorea deltoidea, Angelica glauca (Choru), etc.\n
    </string>
    <string name="textviewfloral4">
   \n\t\t<b><u>3. Sub-Alpine and Alpine Zones of Uttarakhand</u></b>
The altitude above 3,000 metres is generally considered a zone of sub-alpine and alpine
vegetation. The tree species are represented by Pinus wallichiana,
Abies pindrow, Prunus cornuta, Acer caesium, Betula utilis (Bhoj Patra)
and Salix sp. Species of the genera Cotoneaster, Rosa, Berberis,
Ribes, Junipers, Rhododendron anthropogenic, Rhododendron
campanulas are the shrubby components of the zone. \nThe herbaceous
vegetation is represented by a number of species of genera Po
ten till, Primula, Aster, Saxifrage, Achaean, Delphinium,
Polygonal,Corydalis, Pleurospermum, Meconopsis, Pedicularis,
Saussurea, Rheum, Silene, etc. The Bugyals of this zone are well
known for a rich and diversified flora. Plant species like
Nardostachys grand flora (Jatamansi), Podophyllum hexandrum
(Himalayan May-Apple, Papri), Picrorhiza kurrooa (Kutaki), Gentian
burro, Armenia benthonic (Bal char), Rheum moorcroftianum \n</string>
    <string name="textviewfaunal1">
        \n\t\t<b><u>Faunal Diversity</u></b>
A total of 4907 faunal species have been reported which include 3948 invetrebrate fauna and
959 vetrebrate fauna.The fauna exhibits an admixture of Oriental, Palaerectic and IndoSTXMalayan elements. It is home to many endemic and threatened species of both vertebrates and invertberates.\n \nMajor fauna
in the region are Himalayan Bear, Musk Deer, the wild Goat Ghoral, Bharal or Blue Goat,
Wolves, Snow Leopards and varieties of deer such as Barking Deer. Avifauna in the region is
regarded as one of the richest in the sub-continent, with over 500 species of birds.\n
\nWell Known famous Jim Corbett National Park is one of the major habitation of the flora and
fauna in the state. The Royal Bengal Tigers are also found here. The Rajaji National Park which is
a rainforest area is known for its Elephants and the Valley of Flowers National Park which is an
alpine forest and has a number of herbs, shrubs, roses and a variety of Rhododendrons. \n
\nApart from these National Parks in state are the Nanda Devi National Park, Govind National Park
and Gangotri National Park. Such parks are habitat of variety of wild animals like Tigers,
Leopards, Langurs and different species of Deers. A number of birds are also found here, many
of which are migratory birds. \n
\n</string>
    <string name="textviewfaunal2">
   \n\t\t\nThe sub-alpine zones of Almora and outskirts are a natural sanctuary for leopard,
Langur, Himalayan black bear, kakar, goral etc. Whereas the high altitude zones abound musk
deer, popularly called Kastura Mrig, snow leopard, blue sheep, thar etc. The entire zone is rich
in a remarkable variety of birds possessing plumage of magnificent design and colours like
peacock, which include grey quail, Kala Titar, Whistling thrush, Chakor, monal pheasant cheer
pheasant, koklas pheasant etc.</string>
    <string name="textviewfntl1">
        \n\t\t<b><u>Constitution of the Board</u></b>\n
\n\t\tAs per the Section 22 of the Biological Diversity Act, 2002, every State Government is to establish State
Biodiversity Board. Accordingly, the Government of Uttarakhand constituted the State Biodiversity Board,
Uttarakhand vide Govt. Notification No. 1773/X-2-2006-8(83)/2001 dated 01.04.2006.\n
\nFollowing the constitution of the Board, the Government of Uttarakhand in exercise of the powers
conferred under Section 22 (4) (a) of the Biological Diversity Act, 2002, nominated Dr. B.S. Barfal, Retd.
Principal Chief Conservator of Forests, Uttarakhand as the Chairman of the Board for an initial term of 3
years, vide Govt. Notification No. 1767/X-3-2009-8(83)/2001 T.C. dated 08.01.2010.\n
\nThe Board was reconstituted vide Govt. Notification No. 256/X-3-2011-8(83)/2001 T.C. dated 22.03.2011
 in the following manner:\n
Chairman
\n\tNominated by the Government.
\nEx-Officio Members
\n\t1. Secretary, Forest and Environment, Govt. of Uttarakhand.
\n\t2. Principal Chief Conservator of Forests (PCCF), Uttarakhand.
\n\t3. Vice Chancellor, Govind Ballabh Pant University of Agriculture and Technology, Pantnagar.
\n\t4. Director, Uttarakhand Council of Science and Technology, Dehradun
\n\t5. An officer of the rank of Chief Conservator of Forest (On Deputation)- Member-Secretary\n
    \nExpert Members (Non Governmental)
\n\t1. Director, G.B. Pant Institute of Himalayan Environment and Development, Kosi Katarmal, Almora,
Uttarakhand.
\n\t2. Director, Forest Research Institute, MoEF, Govt. of India, Dehradun, Uttarakhand.
\n\t3. Director, Wild Life Institute of India, Dehradun.
\n\t4. Joint Director, Botanical Survey of India, Dehradun or his nominee.
\n\t5. Representative of Non Governmental Organization nominated by the State Government.\n</string>
    <string name="textviewfntl2">
        \n\t\t<b><u>Functions of the Board</u></b>\n
\nAs per section 23 of the Biological Diversity Act, 2002 the functions of the State Biodiversity Board shall be
to:
\n\t1. Advise the State Government, subject to any guidelines issued by the Central Government, on matters
relating to the conservation of biodiversity, sustainable use of its components and equitable sharing of
the benefits arising out of the utilization of biological resources.
\n\t2. Regulate by granting of approvals or otherwise requests for commercial utilization or bio-survey and
bio-utilization of any biological resource by Indians.
\n\t3. Perform such other functions as may be necessary to carry out the provisions of this act or as may be
prescribed by the State Government\n</string>
    <string name="textviewcul1">
        \n\t\t<b><u>Know About The Culture of Uttarakhand</u></b>\n
    \nUttarakhand, also known as Dev Bhoomi, has been the centre of religious and spiritual knowledge for ages. The history and culture of Uttarakhand are deeply connected with religion and celebrated everywhere. Many cultures and ethnicities coexist here with peace and harmony. Most of the state is divided into two regions named Garhwal and Kumaon. It is also home to Jaunsaries, Tibetan refugees, Bokshas, among others.\n

        \n<b><u>Culture</u></b>\n

    \nUttarakhand has a ‘Pahari’ culture. Folk dance, music and festivals are a huge part of Uttarakhand culture. The land is blessed with the beauty of the Himalayas and ancient temples.\n

        \n<b><u>Festivals</u></b>\n

    \nThe typical Hindu festivals such as Diwali, Holi and Navratri are celebrated here with much zeal. Along with this, the Garhwali culture has its festivals such as:\n

    \nHarela parv, phooldei, basant panchama, khichdi sankrant, ganga Dussehra.\n

    \nHarela parv is celebrated in Kumaon as the first day of the monsoon. It is followed by the festival bhitauli, celebrating the seeds sown by Kumaoni women and the harvest time.\n

    \nIgaas is another Garhwali festival; it is celebrated a few days after Diwali and is also known as Garhwali Diwali. The history behind igaas is that the men of Garhwali families who worked in the Army couldn’t come off duty on Diwali. So, they would go home a few days after it, and their families would celebrate Diwali all over again to celebrate their safe homecoming.\n

    \n<b><u>Folk Dance And Music</u></b>\n

    \nUttarakhand religious gatherings would be incomplete without folk songs and dancing. So the people hold their culture in high regard and celebrate together.\n

    \nSome of the folk songs are:\n

   \nJagars are a form of religious offering to our ancestors and their ghosts. Epics, such as Mahabharata and Ramayana, are recited. It is said the gods come down to earth and dance along with the people.\n

    \nOther forms of folk music are Mangal geet that are played during wedding ceremonies.\n

    \n<b><u>Food</u></b>\n

    \nMost Garhwali cuisine revolves around plant-based items that can be grown in the mountains. They also need nutritious food that will keep them warm during the harsh winter months.\n

    \nHere are some of the famous Garhwali foods:\n
   \nUrad dal ke pakode: These are the spicy pakoras made from dal with spices. It is a dish that is popular in every garhwali household. It is specially made on days of celebration such as birthdays, weddings etc.\n

    \nChainsasa: It is made with grinding black gram dal, then it is roasted along with spices before adding water. It is consumed with rice and mango pickle.\n

    \nBhang ki chutney: It is a chutney made from roasted bhang seeds with spices, cumin ginger and lemon juice. It is a sour chutney that goes with all garhwali foods.\n

    \n<b><u>Traditional Clothing</u></b>\n

    \nTraditional Garhwali outfits are vibrant, made with thick materials and unique patterns.\n

    \n<b><u>Men</u></b>\n

    \nMen wear a kurta and pyjama and a koti on top of the kurta. A Koti is a form of wool coat made in Garhwal to keep the cold winds at bay.\n

    \n<b><u>Women</u></b>\n

    \nThe women wear colourful headscarves to protect their faces from the sun, a loose shirt is worn and on top of that a colourful Koti. In addition, a Ghagra or lehenga made of wool or cotton is also worn during these events.\n

    \nIn Kumaoni culture, during weddings, the bride wears a red and sacred golden head covering known as the pichora.\n

    \nLong ‘ naths ’ are worn by both kumaoni and Garhwali women, and they are made out of gold, red and white beads that are auspicious and celebrate the longevity of their marital life.\n

    \nGarhwali women wear a necklace like the modern-day choker; it is called a ‘gul band’.\n

    \nUttarakhand is a land of many cultures and festivals. People from all over the country have settled down here and make the land richer with cultural history. It is the perfect place for anyone who wants to learn more about the Hindu religion or for the breathtaking views of the Himalayas.\n
    </string>
    <string-array name="Categories">
        <item>Categories</item>
        <item>Floral</item>
        <item>Faunal</item>
    </string-array>
</resources>